We're going to start today, today's דף daf is נ"א. nun aleph.
We start the new משנה, mishna, לא הטמינו מבעוד יום. lo hismanu
m’bo yom. So now we obviously know this פרק perek is devoted
to insulating things before שבת Shabbat and you're not allowed to do
that with things that add heat, but you are allowed to do
it with things that preserve heat. And we sort of mentioned in
passing about removing the pot and putting it back, that if you
had insulated it from before שבת Shabbat with something that preserves heat,
you're allowed to take it and restore it on שבת. Shabbat. But
we're now going to see that yes, if you insulated something before
שבת, Shabbat, a hot pot
in something that
preserves heat, you're allowed to remove it on שבת Shabbat and put
it back into the insulation, but you are not allowed to from
the outset insulate it on שבת Shabbat in something even if it
only retains the heat. So that will be what this משנה mishna
says. Let's take a look. לא הטמינו מבעוד יום, lo hismanu m’bo
yom, if you did not cover it, insulate it from the day
before, לא יטמיננו משתחשך, lo yitmi’nenu m’shetechshach, you cannot cover it once
it already gets to be שבת Shabbat even if it's only something
that just retains the heat. Now why is that? The גמרא Gemara
earlier said and רש"י Rashi refers this to a גמרא Gemara earlier.
If you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, because the reason you
can't store it on ערב שבת Erev Shabbat in something that adds
heat is that the classic thing that adds heat is hot coals
or hot ashes, and we're concerned you'll stir it. But what should
be the problem about storing it in something that retains heat? Something
that retains heat, there could be, what problem could that lead to?
I mean, so let's take a look at what רש"י Rashi says.
לא יטמיננו משתחשך, lo yitmi’nenu m’shetechshach, רש"י Rashi says,
הפרשנו טעמא בפרק ב', ha’peirashnu ta’ama b’perek bet, the explanation was given
in the second chapter way back, like about 20 דפים dappim ago,
מפני מה אמרו אין טומנין בדבר שאינו מוסיף הבל, mipnei ma amru
ein tomnin b’davar she’aino mosif hevel, why can you not insulate something
on שבת Shabbat itself in something even if it doesn't add heat,
even if it only retains
heat? משתחשך, m’shetechshach, once it's already dark, גזירה שמא ירתיח, g’zeira shema
yartiyach, we're afraid that you will heat up the pot. This is
quite fascinating. Normally what we're afraid you'll do is like inadvertently. There
you are, you've got it with the hot ashes and you'll stir
the ashes a little bit because inadvertently you've got your pot on
a fire and you'll forget and you'll stir the coals. And therefore
that's what all the discussion of all these two chapters had been,
right? You know, covering the coals and not surrounding it with hot
ashes or with anything that adds heat. Here we're afraid that on
שבת Shabbat itself, if you come to from the very, you know,
it hasn't been in any setup before שבת, Shabbat, it's שבת Shabbat
itself, you haven't done anything before שבת Shabbat and now you want
to wrap it in something that preserves the heat. Well, if you're
wrapping it in something that preserves the heat, it's got to be
pretty hot to start with in order for it to be worth
the effort, right? I mean, if the stuff isn't hot and you're
only preserving the heat, so you've got this pot that's already on
שבת Shabbat itself, so it's already cooled off a bit, and you're
trying to preserve the heat, you say, you know what I better
do, I better put it on the fire first for a few
minutes, get it, you know, heated up a bit so then I
can wrap it in the stuff that'll preserve the heat and then
that'll be worth the effort. So we're afraid, so it's quite fascinating
because you would think something like that would not be inadvertent, something
like that, you know, you'd have to be really aware of what
you're doing. But who knows, you know, sometimes you get so caught
up in an activity that you forget, you know, the larger context,
you forget it's שבת. Shabbat. You're so focused on I've got guests
coming, this thing is cold, I've got to preserve the heat, let
me put it on the fire first, and somehow you forget it's
שבת. Shabbat. So therefore we did not want you on שבת Shabbat
itself to initially wrap it in something that just preserves the heat
because we were afraid that that would lead you to heat it
up beforehand. Okay, so let's take a look now as the משנה
mishna continues. כסהו ונתגלה, kiseihu v’nitgaleh, now if you covered it on
ערב שבת Erev Shabbat and it got exposed, מותר לכסותו, mutar l’chasoto,
then you can re-cover it. And as תוספות Tosafot points out and
it was pretty implicit from the גמרא Gemara before, it's not only
if it accidentally got uncovered, you're allowed to remove it and then
restore it. So you can restore it to a state of being
insulated from before שבת, Shabbat, but you cannot do that from the
outset. ממלא את הקיתון ונותן לתוך הכר או לתוך הכסת. memalei et
ha’kiton v’noten l’toch ha’kar o l’toch ha’keset. Now you can also fill
some flask or some type of a vessel with water and put
it in the, you know, under the pillow or the blanket. Now
what's the point of that? To keep it warm? Normally water wouldn't
be warm. So that's going to be in a discussion in the
גמרא Gemara from the very outset about actually insulating things to keep
them cool, to protect them from the sun and from the heat.
And is there an, are you, is it a problem to insulate
something to keep it cool? So let's take a look because that's
what the גמרא, Gemara, well let's take a look because that's what
the גמרא Gemara assumes and the גמרא Gemara jumps on that from
the very outset. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel, said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda שמואל, Shmuel, I know you could
read it another way but let's read the גמרא. Gemara. מותר להטמין
את הצונן, mutar l’hatmin et ha’tzonin, you can, you can insulate something
that's cold. Like what would be the point of that? רש"י Rashi
says, כדי שלא יחמו בחמה, kedei she’lo yeichamu ba’chama, so it doesn't
get hot in the sun. So it's not like you want it
to stay cold, but you want to keep it from getting warmer?
Like Michael saying, maybe it means it's cold but you don't want
it to get any colder. But okay, the גמרא Gemara so clearly
is going to understand and רש"י Rashi understands that the issue here
is you want to keep it cold. אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav
Yosef, מאי קמשמע לן, mai k’mashma lan, why is that a חידוש?
chidush? תנינא, tnina, we taught it in our משנה, mishna, ממלא אדם
קיתון ונותן לתוך הכר או לתוך הכסת, memalei adam kiton v’noten l’toch
ha’kar o l’toch ha’keset,
you can fill up a flask of water and put it in
the, you know, under the blanket, under the pillow.
אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said, טובא קמשמע לן,
tuva k’mashma lan, no, it's telling us something a lot, something we
would not have figured out from the משנה mishna itself. דאי ממתניתין,
de-im mimatnisin, had I just had the משנה, Mishnah, הוה אמינא, hava
amina, I would have thought, הני מילי, hanei milei, דבר שאין דרכו
להטמין, davar she'ein darko lehatmin, that's something that you normally don't insulate,
אבל דבר שדרכו להטמין, aval davar shedarko lehatmin,
something you normally insulate, לא, lo, that would not be acceptable, קמשמע
לן, kamashmalan, it's telling us otherwise. Now what does it mean you
would not normally insulate? So if you take a look at why
would water be different? Take a look at רש"י Rashi says four
lines into the רש"י Rashi on the גמרא, Gemara, כגון מים צוננים
שאין דרכן להטמין תחת כר וכסת לחממם שאין מתחממים בכך יכול לבוא
למיגזר. kegon mayim tzonin she'ein darkan lehatmin tachas kar vakeses lechamimam she'ein
mischammemim bechach yachol lavo lemigzar.
So the point is like this that I might have thought that
look the whole issue here of wrapping it in something is a
concern that you might come to heat it up. So obviously there
would be no concern if you're dealing with cold things. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says even so again this is how רש"י Rashi
is reading that the purpose of your insulating in the גמרא's Gemara
discussion is to keep it cold. But even if that's true, I
could have distinguished between two cases. I could have said if you
want to insulate something to keep it cold, that's fine if it's
a type of thing that you would never under other circumstances insulate
or rarely insulate to keep warm, like water. Now that I find
a little funny, I mean water you would if you had hot
water you would want to keep it warm, but anyway, but maybe
you're here trying to just, you know, but maybe if you had
cold water you would never try to preserve you'd never try to
preserve the heat. Okay, whereas if something that right now maybe you're
trying to keep cold, but in other circumstances you might want to
be keeping warm, then that's easy to confuse. Then the only difference
between the insulating here which is okay and the insulating in another
case which is not okay is what's your intention. In one case
you're trying to keep it cold, right, because you've got to understand
it's hot outside and you put in a certain thing that'll keep
it away from the sun. In another case it's the same degree
of heat but you're trying to keep it warm, so maybe that
we won't allow you to do it for the sake of keeping
it cold because it can be easily confused with an identical situation
where you would wrap it to keep it warm. So that's the
way רש"י Rashi understands the scenario that in both cases you're trying
to keep it cold or you're trying to not get it hotter,
and that's what allows you to insulate. I might have made a
distinction between scenarios where you could have been doing the exact same
thing for the purpose of keeping it warm as opposed to scenarios
where you normally would never do that. But the גמרא Gemara says
no distinction. As long as you're doing it for the sake of
keeping it cold, it's okay. That's the way רש"י Rashi reads the
גמרא. Gemara. Now again what Michael is saying which I realize you
could also have argued is that maybe the argument is not that
you're trying to keep it cold, maybe what you are trying to
keep warm but nevertheless if it's already pretty cold then we allow
you to insulate it because we're not afraid that if it's already
pretty cold you'll come to heat it up. If it's already warm
maybe you'll heat it up more, maybe it's more similar to the
case of getting things hot and so on, if it's already pretty
cold maybe it's not an issue. But that's not the way at
least that רש"י Rashi reads the גמרא. Gemara. רש"י Rashi says if
you're doing it for the sake of keeping it cold that's okay,
if you're doing it for the sake of keeping it warm that's
no good. Yes.
How cold is cold?
Yeah I don't know, good question. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
You said that's the way רש"י Rashi reads it, someone else read
it differently?
I don't know, but I agree with you that the גמרא Gemara
in theory could have been read differently. Let's read the גמרא Gemara
continues. Okay.
אמר רב הונא אמר רבי, Amar Rav Huna amar Rebbe, אסור להטמין
את הצונן, assur lehatmin es hatzonin, you cannot insulate something cold. והתניא
רבי התיר להטמין את הצונן, vehatanya Rebbe hitir lehatmin es hatzonin, so
how could that be a version of it's something in the name
of רבי, Rebbe, we have another statement that רבי Rebbe allowed somebody
to insulate something cold. לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא
מקמי דשמעה מרבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי הא לבתר דשמעה מרבי ישמעאל
בר רבי יוסי. ha mikamei deshamaei mei-Rebbe Yishmael bar Rebbe Yossi ha
lebasar deshamaei mei-Rebbe Yishmael bar Rebbe Yossi. רבי Rebbe reversed himself, one
was before he heard it from רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי, Rebbe
Yishmael bar Rebbe Yossi, the other's after. Where's this רבי ישמעאל בר
רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yishmael bar Rebbe Yossi, we haven't mentioned him yet.
So we have a
ברייתא. braisa. כי הא דיתיב רבי, ki had deyasiv Rebbe, רבי Rebbe
was sitting ואמר, ve-amar, אסור להטמין את הצונן, assur lehatmin es hatzonin,
you cannot insulate something cold. אמר לפניו רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי,
amar lefanev Rebbe Yishmael bar Rebbe Yossi, אבא אבא Abba Abba my
father רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yossi, התיר להטמין את הצונן, hitir lehatmin es
hatzonin, he allowed you to insulate things that were cold. אמר, amar,
so רבי Rebbe said, כבר הורה זקן, kvar hora zaken, ah so
the elder already פסקנ'ד, poskened, so I take it back. Okay you
can insulate things that are cold. Sounded like some refrigerator. Well that's
a good point actually. I guess how cold might be wrapped around.
But anyway. All right, good point. So אמר רב פפא, amar Rav
Pappa, בא וראה כמה מחבבין זה לזה, bo re'ei kama mechabevin ze
la-ze, see how much the sages were like, you know,
held dear one another. שאילו רבי יוסי קיים, she-ilu Rebbe Yossi kayam,
when רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi was alive היה כפוף ויושב לפני רבי,
haya kofuf veyoshev lifnei Rebbe, he would sit in a sort of,
you know, bent down, he would subject himself to רבי. Rebbe. רבי
Rebbe would be the גדול gadol and he would and you know
and he would adopt a subservient position. והא רבי ישמעאל בר רבי
יוסי דממלא מקום אבותיו הוה, veha Rebbe Yishmael bar Rebbe Yossi dememale
makom avosav hava, and how do I know that? Because I know
רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי Rebbe Yishmael bar Rebbe Yossi was just
as great of a גדול gadol as his father as רבי יוסי,
Rebbe Yossi, he filled the place of his father וכפוף ויושב לפני
רבי, vekofuf veyoshev lifnei Rebbe, and when he sat in front of
רבי, Rebbe, right, the story he was sitting in a, you know,
in a subservient position. So obviously his father was as well. And
nevertheless, even when רבי יוסי Rebbe Yossi was alive that was true.
וקאמר, vekamar, כבר הורה זקן, kvar hora zaken, and then after he
told him what his father said, רבי Rebbe said, oh so the
elder already. for the sake of רבי יוסי's. Rabbi Yose Now what's
the logic before about this? So רש"י Rashi says, well, there's a
difference between who is the bigger תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and who
had more sort of power. That רבי Rebbe was the נשיא, nasi,
רבי Rebbe was in charge. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose adopted a
subservient position because you show respect for, you know,
for יהודה הנשיא Yehuda HaNasi who was the נשיא, nasi, even if
you're the bigger תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, but you adopt a position
obviously of subservience and respect. But רבי Rebbe himself who acknowledged that
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose was the bigger תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, so
maybe as long as רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose was alive, you know,
you have to maintain authority and so on, but once רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose had passed away, he was willing to step aside for
the ruling of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, acknowledging that רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose was the greater sage. That's the way רש"י Rashi says which
makes a lot of sense. תוספות Tosafot actually says that רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose actually was a lesser sage. They're dealing with another גמרא
Gemara that says רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose was greater, תוספות Tosafot says
maybe it depends at what stage of רבי's Rebbe career and so
on. So that makes the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara even more
startling. If רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose was a lesser sage, then why
is רבי Rebbe standing aside out of honor for a רבי יוסי's
Rabbi Yose position? So that's not so clear. I mean, but according
to רש"י Rashi it makes a lot of sense. Okay. Yes.
There's absolutely no reason for this to be in the
גמרא. Gemara. This little paragraph except to show this הלכה. halacha. Right.
You just talked about a הלכה halacha that he took it back,
so why even tell us that?
Right, that the גמרא Gemara takes a minute to step aside to
point this out, right, it's quite beautiful, absolutely.
Okay. אמר ליה רב נחמן לדר עבדיה, Amar lei Rav Nachman ledar
avdei, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to דרו Daru his
servant, אטמין לי צוני, Atmin li tzonei, go ahead and insulate for
me this cold water, and by the way, ואייתי לי מיא דאחים
כפילא ארמאה, V'aisei li maya de'achim kfela armayei, and bring me water
that's been heated up by a non-Jewish chef. I don't know why
it had to be a chef, but that was the case.
Now, שמע רבי אמי ואיקפיד, Shama Rabbi Ammi ve'ikpid,
so רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi heard about this and he got, he
took offense. How could he rule this way? So there's two, each
one of these is a חידוש. chiddush. אמר רב יוסף מאי טעמא
איקפיד, Amar Rav Yosef, mai ta'ama ikpid,
why are you upset at him? Why, you don't like his rulings?
כרבותיה עביד, Ke'rabosei avid,
רב נחמן Rav Nachman is going like his
רבנים. rebbeim. Right. No, he said, I'm sorry, you're right, רב נחמן,
Rav Nachman, thank you, רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. He's going like his
רבנים. rebbeim.
חדא כרב וחדא כשמואל, Chada keRav v'chada keShmuel, one like רב Rav
and one like שמואל. Shmuel. כשמואל דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מותר
להטמין את הצוני, KeShmuel d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, mutar l'hatmin es
hatzonei, because number one in terms of insulating cold things on שבת,
Shabbat, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of שמואל
Shmuel that you're allowed to insulate cold things. וכרב, V'keRav, and his
other רבי Rebbe was רב, Rav, and he goes like רב, Rav,
דאמר רב שמואל בר רב יצחק אמר רב כל שנאכל כמו שהוא
חי אין בו משום בישולי נכרים. D'amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak
amar Rav, kol she'ne'echal k'mo shehu chai ein bo mishum bishulei nochrim.
So the second thing of heated up water was a separate issue.
It wasn't a שבת Shabbat issue, although you could wonder like maybe
if it was the chef and he did it for other people
then maybe you can benefit from it. It raises interesting questions of
benefiting from the מלאכה melacha of a non-Jew on שבת. Shabbat. But
whether it was or wasn't שבת, Shabbat, the issue wasn't the שבת
Shabbat aspect. The issue was why can you eat something that was
cooked by a non-Jew? There's a problem about בישולי גויים, bishulei goyim,
about food that was cooked by a non-Jew. So he says, ah,
but that he's going like רב Rav because רב Rav says if
the thing could have been eaten raw, it doesn't have the problem
of בישול גויים, bishul goyim, of בישול עכו"ם. bishul akum. So that's
why he allowed himself to drink the hot water that was heated
by the non-Jew, it wasn't a בישול עכו"ם bishul akum problem. So
why are you upset at him? So the גמרא Gemara says, והוא
סבר, V'hu savar, and the reason that רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi was
upset was because he felt אדם חשוב שאני, Adam chashuv shani, an
important person should act differently. An important person maybe should act in
a higher standard, should appreciate that his actions are interpreted by people
and, you know, they don't go by strict הלכה, halacha, they go
by their perceived norms. And therefore if somebody is acting a certain
way, they'll either think lesser of him or they'll think that that
gives them an allowance to themselves act leniently in areas where it's
not allowed. And you know, this is by the way an important
point. First of all, there is issues about generally when there's a
certain perception about that something is forbidden,
how much do you have to sort of be sensitive to that
perception, right? Or do you, you know, or should you just do
what's right and it's not your business if people don't understand what's
מותר mutar or what's אסור? assur? So you know רב משה Rav
Moshe was asked about this once about מראית עין. marit ayin. Like,
do I have to be concerned about מראית עין marit ayin if
I'm doing something that technically that is מותר mutar but that people
think is אסור? assur? And רב משה Rav Moshe said you don't
have to worry about מראית עין. marit ayin. מראית עין marit ayin
is when everybody knows what the problem is and there's a confusion
about the facts. You know, I go ahead and I'm eating a,
you know, fake bacon bits and people think it's real bacon, or
I'm eating my hamburger with soy cheese on it. So everybody knows
the הלכה, halacha, it's just there's a confusion about the facts. You
don't want to look like you're violating a הלכה. halacha. Okay, that's
מראית עין. marit ayin. Here there's an actual misunderstanding about what the
הלכה halacha is. Right? So the answer to that is not to
give in to ignorance, but it's to educate people. So if people
think that it's wrong and it's really right, so you should let
them know that it's right.
Yes, and according to רב משה, Reb Moshe, you're not supposed to
eat like fake bacon bits?
Well, unless, unless people are aware about that reality. Like when the,
you know, when the coffee whitener just came out, the פרווה pareve
coffee whitener, they all said you had to have the actual like
box on the table itself. Now that everybody knows that there's פרווה
pareve coffee whitener, you don't have to. So a lot of it
is a function of what people's knowledge and awareness of these things
are. Anyway, but that's in terms of מראית עין. maris ayin. There
still are other realities that there's like strongly ingrained community standards, which
are on things that are not הלכה, halacha, and nevertheless, you know,
there's like, you know, there are these, you know, strongly ingrained perceptions,
and to what degree do you want to be acting in ways
that, you know, at least people will perceive, you know, that you
are doing something wrong? And particularly if you're an אדם חשוב, adam
chashuv, and then that'll lead to a, you know, to thinking less
of you or to thinking or to thinking that giving them like
I said an allowance to themselves acting incorrectly. So it is interesting
that this idea that in some areas the higher standard for an
אדם חשוב. adam chashuv. You know, people that are rabbis or my
students who are training to be rabbis or whatever, you know, it's
an issue even in completely non-הלכתי halachic areas, you know, like a
rabbi has to be concerned about, you know, how you walk, you
know, you know, on a Sunday outside in the street, you know,
you're going around in your shorts and t-shirt or whatever, you know,
there are these different perceptions of what we expect from people, you
know, from אדם חשוב adam chashuv and people in, you know, representing
תורה. Torah. So that is an issue he said even if technically
it was allowed. Raises interesting questions about, you know, how that plays
out in practice. Yes.
And how does he interpret this גמרא Gemara then? Because רב אמי
Rav Ami was saying that he should have acted differently. This is
a case where he's saying...
No, so he says why was רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, why
is רב אמי, Rav Ami, why is רב אמי Rav Ami getting
upset, you know? What he did was completely legitimate. And the answer
was רב אמי Rav Ami was upset because he expected more from...
I know, I'm saying based on that, wouldn't we have expected רב
משה Reb Moshe to say, 'Yeah, you're an אדם חשוב'...
adam chashuv No, so, whatever, he wasn't talking about an אדם חשוב.
adam chashuv. Like I said, there's one issue about מראית עין maris
ayin which applies to everybody on the planet, and then there's the
question about what types of things fall into the אדם חשוב adam
chashuv category. So decide what's an אדם חשוב adam chashuv then, and
then... Maybe! But not everything falls into that category. But yes, there
are some things that it would be that would fall into that
אדם חשוב adam chashuv category.
We actually פסקן pasken
this about the אדם חשוב שאני? adam chashuv shani? No, but absolutely,
that's one of the major היתרים heterim for בישול עכו"ם bishul akum
is if it could be eaten raw. But it's interesting questions nowadays
in the advent of things like sushi and even like steak tartare,
what do you mean could be eaten raw? You know, and so
I mean to say fish, there's no longer a problem about בישול
עכו"ם bishul akum because everybody eats raw fish, maybe. Some people want
to say that. Okay, let's take a look now as the גמרא
Gemara continues. תנו רבנן. Tana rabbanan. So that's about, that's about storing
cold things, which רש"י Rashi says the point is if it's for
the purpose of keeping it cold, it's allowed, and even if under
other circumstances you would store the same object for the purpose of
keeping it warm, if you're doing it for the purpose of keeping
it cold, it's not a problem. And a perfect example of this
would be using a thermos. A thermos is perfect, I keep on
telling you this joke, which is a stupid joke, but anyway, it's
like a thermos is great, it keeps hot things hot and cold
things cold, but how does it know? So anyway, but anyway, so
you can put things in a thermos to keep it cold, that's
fine, but even though that exact same type of a context you
might use in another scenario to keep things warm, right? But a
thermos, now again by the thermos by the way raises other questions
which רב משה Reb Moshe deals with, which is how much do
you פסקן pasken an issue of הטמנה hatmana if it's actually just
a container? Meaning, if I put something in a metal pan, I
don't consider it to be הטמנה, hatmana, right? Even if maybe the
metal does a decent job of retaining the heat, right? If I'm
transferring my thing from my, you know, from I served my hot
chicken, I put on the table, then I'm transferring it back and
I'm putting it into some type of a metal pan that I'm
going to keep it in, I don't say oh that's הטמנה בדבר
המוסיף הבל hatmana b'davar she'mosif hevel because it's a container. So what
would you say about a thermos? Is a thermos a container or
is a thermos הטמנה? hatmana? So רב משה Reb Moshe has a
תשובה teshuvah about that.
But what I'm saying is like,
you know, if we're worried about שמא ירתיח, shema yartiyach, that makes
more sense if it's like a pot, you know, you keep it
in your pot, then you can put the same pot on the
fire, but here if it's in a thermos and שמא ירתיח shema
yartiyach you'd have to consciously put it into another thing and then
put that on the fire, isn't that like a separate move?
One more time, no, הטמנה hatmana is an act that you do
about putting insulation around the container that it's in, not directly around
the food. So the container itself doesn't count as the insulation.
Well, right, but we're worried about why can't you do it on
שבת Shabbat because we're worried about שמא ירתיח. shema yartiyach. So if
I put something in my thermos, in other words I'd say it's
different than putting it in your pot that you can
put on the fire,
but a thermos you can't put on a fire.
Alright, it could be. It also goes to the question about how
much do you factor in the motivation for the תקנה takkana into
the exact parameters of the תקנה? takkana? Very often that's just of
historical interest; the actual formal parameters are not directly linked to it.
Yes.
Can you use a thermos for hot as well?
So I knew that was going to raise, I believe רב משה
Reb Moshe says it's okay because it's just a container, it's not
considered to be something external to the container, but I have to
double-check. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן:
Tana rabbanan: אף על פי שאמרו אין טומנין אפילו בדבר שאינו מוסיף
הבל, Af al pi she'amru ein tomnin afilu b'davar she'eino mosif hevel,
although they said you cannot do הטמנה hatmana even in something that
does not add heat. once it gets dark, right? From before שבת
Shabbos, *Shabbos* you can do it in stuff that are that that
is that doesn't add heat, but once it gets dark you can't
do an initial הטמנה hatmana, *hatmanah* to begin with. But אם בא
להוסיף מוסיף *im ba lehosif mosif*. However, if you've already got it
insulated, you can add additional insulation. So you've got your stuff wrapped
in your, you know, wool or whatever it is from before שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos* and you want to add more wool on top to
preserve the heat even more. That's okay, that's not like an initial
putting it in insulation, that's adding to the existing scenario. Okay, כיצד
הוא עושה *keitzad hu oseh*? What are you, what can you do?
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר נוטל את הסדינין ומניח סגלופקרין או נוטל
את הסגלופקרין ומניח את הסדינין *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer notel es
hasadinim umeniach saglofkarin o notel es haglofkarin umeniach es hasadinim*. So סדינין
*sadinim* are sheets, סגלופקרין *saglofkarin* is another type of a like a
thick cover that does even a better job of preserving the heat.
So he says you can exchange the top covering of it. You
can remove the thick cover and put on a thinner cover or
remove the thin cover and put up a thicker cover. So all
of that is okay. Now, because you're basically you have an existing
insulation and you're just adding to it or slightly adjusting it. Now,
one position in תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* actually says that רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* it's not כיצד הוא עושה *keitzad hu
oseh*, it's רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* actually is
arguing. Because the first position says you can leave everything exactly the
way you have it and then add to it. Then you're just
building on an existing scenario. But to actually remove something and replace
it with something else, right, and in the act of removing you're
exposing the pot, maybe that would be considered like a new הטמנה
hatmana *hatmanah*, right? It's not like you have everything as it was
and you just increased it. You actually took something away, exposed the
pot, put something new on, maybe that's a new הטמנה *hatmanah*. So
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* says I'm okay with
that as well. Basically that's just adjusting, that's not really something new
from the outset. So that would actually be okay and that has
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* arguing. So it's a
question is he arguing or clarifying the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*, but
according to him adjusting is okay, not just adding.
Can you do that on the חזרה *chazarah* too? I took it
out, I put it back, which you're allowed to do.
What on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* from the stove? Yeah, you can do
חזרה *chazarah* from one flame to another. That actually is a good
point that it's worth making a parallel. We won't do it now
but it's worth looking at a parallel about the idea that Mike
is correct that there is these two parallel הלכות halachos *halachos*, right?
You keep something on the flame from before שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* on
a גרופה וקטומה grufa u'ketuma *gerufah u'ketumah*, you can remove it and
put it back on. But you can't put something initially on a
flame on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*, okay? And not a flame. This is
like a flame that's covered with a בלעך *blech*, okay? Nowadays we
can, you know, you put some things on like a hot plate
that's even better than a בלעך *blech*, I won't get into that.
But basically assume you've got a בלעך *blech* over your flame, you
cannot initially put something on that on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*, but if
it was on there from שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* began, you take it
off and then if you're still let's say holding onto it and
you haven't set it down or some type of thing like that,
you put it back on. So that's the same idea that continuing
the process is okay. חזרה *chazarah* is okay, doing it initially is
not good. When you take it and you put it in the
fridge and then you wake up the next morning you want to
put it on, that's like doing it initially, that's not a continuation
of the process. Okay, but
so that's when it comes to, you're right, חזרה *chazarah*.
Here same idea. And then you put more of a whatever it
is on it, right?
I'll make the parallel in a minute. That's that case. So Mike's
correct. Here same idea. You can take it from the insulation and
put it back to the insulation, but you cannot initially, you know,
go ahead and put it into new insulation. So the fact that
here we're saying that when you are, you can add to the
insulation once it's already there, in a similar way you're right, if
you go ahead you're allowed on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos* to take it
off of one flame, assuming it's fully cooked and it's only a
rabbinic problem and it's still in your hands and you can put
it back on another flame, on a higher flame. So you can
actually do some type of adjustment as long as it's seen as
a continual process. So you are correct to be making that parallel.
Okay, so that's what רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*
says, you can actually adjust it. אבל *aval*, okay, וכן היה רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל אומר *v'chein hayah Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer*, רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* had another leniency and he
would say, לא Lo, אסרו אלא אותו מיחם meicham אבל פינה ממיחם
למיחם מותר *lo asu ela oso meicham aval pina mimeicham l'meicham mutar*.
It's only forbidden if it's in the original thing it was heated
up in. But if you put it into a second vessel—you heat
up some hot water in one pot and then you pour it
into another, you heat up your chicken in one pot you pour
it in another—then you are allowed to insulate the second pot. Why?
Because the second pot now is so cool, it's cooling off, it's
not retained heat, that it's like, you know, we're not concerned that
you're going to reasonably be working to keep it hot, okay? So
therefore, it's funny, like if the whole concern is you might come
to heat it up again, you know, you might say there's a
heightened concern. But this is similar to, and this is what how
Mike I'm sure wanted to explain the first גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about
צונן *sonen*, that even if you're trying to keep it hot, if
the thing is basically cooling off and it's gotten beyond a certain
point and it's already so cold, it's like גארנישט העלפן *gornisht helfen*
so then we're not even so concerned. So if you switch it
to a second, a second vessel, right, so then it's cooling off
much more rapidly, then it's not an issue, okay? So that's
פינה
ממיחם למיחם *pina mimeicham l'meicham*. One minute, right. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
it's actually not just it happens to be cooling off but actually
that act, you are doing an act to cool it off, therefore
we're not so concerned that you're going to be working at heating
it up. Okay, so actually the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it: השתא אקורי קמיקר ליה ארתוחי קמרתח ליה
*hashta akurei k'meiker lei artuchei k'mirtech lei*?
This is by the way just a תוספתא, Tosefta so it's just
throwing in a lot of cases the גמרא Gemara isn't even going
to really bother to discuss it. It's just the last thing it
does in this פרק Perek is gives you a תוספתא with a
lot of rules. So, טמן וכיסה בדבר הניטל בשבת, Tamman vechisa b'davar
hanittal bashabbos, now we get back to the מוקצה Muktzeh issues which
were a focus on this of this פרק. Perek. טמן וכיסה בדבר
הניטל בשבת, Tamman vechisa b'davar hanittal bashabbos, if you if you insulated
and covered it with something that was not מוקצה, Muktzeh, something could
be moved on שבת, Shabbat או טמן בדבר שאינו ניטל בשבת וכיסה
בדבר הניטל בשבת, o tamman b'davar she'eino nittal bashabbos vechisa b'davar hanittal
bashabbos, or let's say you insulated it in מוקצה Muktzeh as long
as you covered it in non מוקצה, Muktzeh, הרי זה נוטל ומחזיר,
harei zeh notel umachzir, not a problem because as long as you
have access from the top, you take it out and you put
it back. Remember, there's an opinion in the משנה Mishnah that says
I don't let you take it out because I'm afraid you'll come
to put it back and the hole will be filled and then
you'll make a new hole, but this ברייתא Braisa is the position
of the חכמים, Chachamim, not concerned with that, you can take it
and put it back as long as you don't have to move
מוקצה. Muktzeh. טמן וכיסה בדבר שאינו ניטל בשבת, Tamman vechisa b'davar she'eino
nittal bashabbos, however, if it's insulated with מוקצה, Muktzeh, או שטמן בדבר
הניטל בשבת וכיסה בדבר שאינו ניטל בשבת, o shetamman b'davar hanittal bashabbos
vechisa b'davar she'eino nittal bashabbos, or even if it's just insulated if
it's insulated surrounded with non מוקצה, Muktzeh, but if it's covered with
מוקצה, Muktzeh, so then how do you get access to it? Now
רש"י Rashi says, what do you mean how do you get access?
As long as he's just remove the stuff on the sides and
get access, right? I mean who cares who cares if the top
is covered with מוקצה Muktzeh if the sides isn't, move the stuff
on the sides and get access. So רש"י Rashi has an explanation
about בסיס bassis which doesn't really work so well. תוספות Tosafot has
a very simple explanation, he says we're talking if you remember before
the משנה Mishnah or the גמרא Gemara wherever mentioned a case what
was in a box. So it's a it's a the pot is
in a box and the box is filled with the insulation. So
therefore if the insulation on the side is not מוקצה, Muktzeh, it
doesn't help you, the only access to the thing is from the
top, so it all matters about whether the top layer is מוקצה
Muktzeh or not. Okay? So if you've got your top layer מוקצה,
Muktzeh, then how do you get access to your pot? You'd have
to move the מוקצה. Muktzeh. So what do you do? אם היה
מגולה מקצתו, Im hayah meguleh miktzato, so if a little bit of
the pot was exposed, fine, נוטל ומחזיר, notel umachzir, grab onto the
exposed part, the מוקצה Muktzeh falls off incidentally, it's טלטול מן הצד,
tiltul min hatzad, no problem. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, but if none
of it was exposed, אינו נוטל ומחזיר, eino notel umachzir, you've got
your stuck, you have no access to the pot because the only
way to get to it would be by moving directly moving the
מוקצה Muktzeh because you could have to actually physically with your hand
move the מוקצה Muktzeh you wouldn't start by grabbing onto the pot
and be indirect, you'd have to move the מוקצה Muktzeh out of
the way. Now maybe you could use your elbows or your foot,
that's another that's not being suggested here but that actually could be
a solution. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yehuda omer: נסורת של פשתן
דקה nesoret shel pishtan dakah as you see this is just a
collection of a lot of different הלכות smacked together, a lot of
quick recapping of things we learned in this פרק. Perek. If you
have very thin like remnants of flax, that you cannot insulate with,
הרי הוא כזבל, harei hu kezavel, that's like excrement which actually adds
heat and you cannot insulate with that. מניחין מיחם על גבי מיחם
וקדירה על גבי קדירה. Manichin meicham al gabi meicham vekdeirah al gabi
kdeirah. Here we have another.
You can put a hot
water pot on top of a hot water one, or a מיחם
meicham is more like metal, קדירה kdeirah is more of a pottery
pot on top of one, אבל לא קדירה על גבי מיחם ומיחם
על גבי קדירה, aval lo kdeirah al gabi meicham umeicham al gabi
kdeirah, but you cannot do one on top of the other, mix
genres. Now רש"י changes the גירסא, girsa, so he says the real
גירסא girsa says and and that's the way we פוסקין poskin is
and you can you can do it, you can do a מיחם
meicham. on a קדירה kdeirah and a קדירה kdeirah on a מיחם.
So the point here is what? The point here is although the
bottom pot is adding heat, that's not considered הטמנה בדבר המוסיף הבל
hatmana b'davar hamosif havel because it's not surrounded by some insulator, just
is on something that's adding heat. And the point is you're allowed
to do it as long as you're even allowed to do it
on
שבת Shabbat. itself if the thing is not going to get to
יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, if it's not going to lead
to an issue of בישול bishul if it's not going to get
so hot that it'll actually lead to cooking the liquid, okay? So
you're putting it on top of something, it's not actually a concern
of הטמנה, it's not a concern of גרופה וקטומה either as it's
not going to get to יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, it's
not a problem.
You spoke about if it's a solid, it gets to what would
be יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, that be a problem?
Yeah, I mean it's true in general you might the definition of
cooking by solids might be different but we tend to be מחמיר
machmir regardless by יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, but it's a
good point. Okay, so anyway you're allowed to do that because it's
not going to be a concern of cooking on שבת Shabbat if
with the qualifier which isn't here but with the qualifier that it's
not going to get to יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, you're
just trying to stop it from getting cooler, if you remember the
גמרא Gemara. before discussed this and it said you're basically trying to
stop it from getting cooler, you're not trying to actually heat it
up, which is interpreted by the פוסקים poskim to mean not only
you're not trying to heat it up but in practice it's not
even going to get to יד סולדת בו. yad soledet bo. So
then it's allowed. Okay, וטח את פיה בבצק, Vetach et piha b'vatzek,
and you also can take some pre-existing dough, you can't make dough
on שבת, Shabbat? and put it around the edge in order to
retain like between the cover and the and the edge in order
to keep the heat in. Okay. ולא בשביל שיחמו אלא בשביל שיהיו
משומרין, Velo bishvil sheyachamu ela bishvil sheyihyu meshumarin, not to get heated
up but so that it shall not lose its heat. So A,
it's not a problem of הטמנה and B, it's not a problem
of בישול bishul because as I said we're assuming it's not going
to get to יד סולדת בו. yad soledet bo. וכשם שאין טומנין
את החמין כך אין טומנין את הצונן *uksheim she'ein tomnin et hachamin
kach ein tomnin et hatzonen* and the same way you can't insulate
hot you can't insulate cold. Rabbi התיר להטמין את הצונן *hetyir lehatmin
et hatzonen* getting back to the discussion between Rabbi allowed you once
he heard it from ישמעאל ברבי יוסי *Yishmael berabbi Yose*. ואין מרסקין
*ve'ein merazkin* now here's a very interesting new הלכה halacha? *halacha*, ואין
מרסקין לא Lo, את השלג ולא את הברד בשבת בשביל שיזובו מימיו
*ve'ein merazkin lo et hasheleg velo et
habarad beshabbat bishvil sheyizovu meimav*. You cannot take snow or hail on
שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* and squeeze it in order to transform it
ואין מרסקין *ve'ein
merazkin* is like סוחטין *sochtin*? Right, in order to transform it into
water so the water should flow, אבל נותן הוא לתוך הכוס או
לתוך הקיתון ואינו חושש *aval notein hu letoch hakos o letoch hakiton
ve'eino choshesh*. But you can put ice into your glass and let
it melt and that's not a problem, it happens by itself. Now
what is this about? Very important question here about what the problem
is which has broad implications for believe it or not מוקצה muktzeh,
*muktzah* on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*, which is there's two approaches here. One
which basically is the approach that the שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* adopts
is that it's a problem that it is like you're creating something.
The problem is that you are actively squeezing it, maybe it's also
like squeezing fruit which just get out the juices, it'll be confused
with that case. So the problem is that you are actively squeezing
it and you're creating something new and it's like I said like
squeezing juices out of fruit. Fine, so that's the only problem is
doing that. If it happened if it happens without you squeezing it,
not a problem. So if you want to let's say put something
by a fire and and you know you want to put your
chicken with congealed gravy by a fire
and the gravy is going to liquefy, no problem, you're not actually
squeezing something and turning it into liquid. And therefore that's the point
of the second part, as long as it happens by itself, no
issue. The other approach says no no no, the issue is not
that it looks like squeezing fruit or that it looks like making
something new. The issue is that the actual result when ice transforms
into liquid is a type of נולד nolad, *nolad*, right? There's a
מוקצה muktzeh. *muktzah* called נולד nolad *nolad*, something new, which might be
like an egg that's laid. So how about something that transforms from
solid to liquid, from frozen to liquid? Is that נולד nolad, *nolad*
or not? So there's an approach of one of the בעלי התוספות
*Ba'alei Hatosafot* that says that it is. And therefore it's not just
a problem about you doing it, it's a problem even if it
happens by itself, even using it after the fact it's a type
of a מוקצה muktzeh. *muktzah*. So why is it okay if it's
in the cup? Because then it immediately dissolves straight into your water.
Like if you have an ice cube in your soda and then
it dissolves into the soda, that's not a נולד nolad. *nolad* problem
because it's not like it ever existed independently. It immediately became part
of the thing it was in, so it never gets its independent
identity. But if your ice actually was in a, you know, a
bowl and turned into water, then that water in the bowl would
be מוקצה muktzeh *muktzah*. Which is a very strict position not only
about ice and water but about נולד *nolad* and you know it
leads to all these questions about like can you know if can
you put
water in your freezer on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat* and make it into
ice? Can you put those you know they you know they sell
these like things for kids, right? Like those like things with sugar
water in them and you put them in and then you turn
them into ice pops, right? And is even that type of a
transformation of a state considered to be a נולד *nolad* issue or
not? So a lot of the books about מוקצה muktzeh *muktzah* or
whatever you know are very much consider this to be נולד *nolad*.
Although if you look in the שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch*, the שולחן
ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* basically rules the first way, that the problem is
to do it actively. The רמ״א *Rema* sort of says if possible
you should maybe be מחמיר *machmir* for the other position. But even
the רמ״א *Rema* is not really פוסק׳ן *poskening* the other way, he's
just saying like it's something maybe to be חושש *choshesh* for. Nevertheless
there's a lot of these people that lot of these פסקים *psakim*
you'll find that treat this thing as נולד *nolad*. I myself am
very skeptical because especially nowadays where it's the transformation is so like
easy and regular between those two states. You know maybe if you
did something more drastic like take something that I'm trying to think
about what would be a more drastic change of state. You know
you condense steam although that wouldn't be good here. I don't know,
I'd have to think about something that doesn't normally transform state so
easily. But anyway, but a lot of a lot of people will
tell you that making something from liquid to to from liquid to
ice or ice to liquid is נולד *nolad*, but that's really not
I would say the simple sense of this גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* nor
the way that the the basic פסק *psak* of the שולחן ערוך
*Shulchan Aruch*. But it is the way that one of the בעלי
התוספות *Ba'alei Hatosafot* does actually read it. With that being said, if
you use the freezer to do something that's not really changing the
state like in my house we like frozen grapes, you should try
it, it's delicious. Anyway, so if you put the grapes in the
freezer before on Friday night and they're frozen by שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*
morning, there I mean in a way you haven't really changed liquid
to solid, you've just sort of like hardened the existing juices that
are in that. That certainly wouldn't be a problem. But there is
interesting discussions about whether that's considered נולד *nolad*.
So I want to make sure so even according to the people
who say it is a problem to change ice into water or
whatever it is, that's only you said if you put it in
the bucket of ice. But if you left it in your water?
Right, that's the second case of the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara*. And if you put that near like your hot water pot
to do that?
Yeah. As long as it's immediately it never exists independently. It's immediately
becoming one with the existing liquid that's in the thing. Okay? So
הדרן עלך במה טומנין *hadran alach bameh tomnin*. That is the end
of that פרק perek, *perek* and with this we end two big
פרקים prakim *prakim*. Cooking, putting stuff on the flame before שבת, Shabbat
putting it back on the flame, putting stuff in insulator, all these
things relating to cooking and also מוקצה, muktzeh, okay, which was a
major part of this. Now we are going to have two more
פרקים prakim before we get to the seventh פרק, which finally turns
us to a look at all the ל"ט מלאכות. lamed-tet melachot. We
have two more פרקים prakim, to go and those are fully developed,
devoted to carrying. So by the time we will have been done
with the first seventy דף daf of שבת, Shabbat. like two months
into שבת, Shabbat. we will have done six פרקים, prakim all of
which are basically devoted, if you remember we started our מסכת masekhet
with carrying, right? So all of which are devoted basically to carrying,
fire, cooking, right, because במה מדליקין, Bameh Madlikin, fire, cooking, and keeping
stuff on the fire. Basically and מוקצה. muktzeh? And that basically is
where almost all of the conversation ironically or not so ironically, I
mean, but anyway, that, I mean עירובין Eruvin is all about carrying,
right? We're going to have a whole מסכת masekhet about carrying. So
if you think about there are ל"ט מלאכות lamed-tet melachot on שבת,
Shabbat? but how much of what we have learned and will continue
to learn is basically about carrying, cooking, fire, and מוקצה. muktzeh Okay?
So the next two פרקים and מוקצה muktzeh is not even one
of the thirty, and מוקצה is not even biblical, right? And keeping
stuff on the fire, a lot of that is rabbinic as well.
Yes, so that last מחלוקת mahloket on שבת. Shabbat. Yes. Having a
snowball fight. Right. Carrying. Liquid? Well, if you don't have an עירוב
eruv you certainly can't do it. That's carrying. The issue is more
about if it's a
type of בונה boneh or
a type of, you know, like putting little pieces together, by making
the snowball and so on. Right, that's a bigger issue about something
like a בונה boneh type of a concern. So yeah, that's a
problem. I mean, we're not dealing with that right now. It's not
a problem because of נולד, you're not squeezing it and getting it
out. The נולד issue is not a carrying issue. It's not from
an עירוב. eruv. It's basically more of a בונה boneh type of
an issue. But what if it's going to dissolve right away anyway?
Then is that בונה boneh if something's not going to be permanent?
Right. It's a question of degree of impermanence. But those types of
things are not so impermanent. I mean, they'll last a little while.
In the last שלג sheleg case, presumably this was שלג sheleg that
was there before שבת Shabbat, and he had in mind otherwise it'd
be מוקצה, right? No, so that's basically a good question which I'll
just say and then we do have to move on, which is,
if you think making ice is נולד, so then why don't we,
how about snow? Would you treat snow as מוקצה? So interestingly people
don't treat snow as מוקצה even those that say that making ice
is a type of נולד. So go figure that out, but snow
is generally not treated as מוקצה that falls on שבת. Shabbat. Okay?
Yeah. So anyway, let's keep on going. Shovel snow from our sidewalk?
That's a different question, whether you can shovel it. But okay, moving
on. במה בהמה יוצאה ובמה אינה יוצאה. Bameh behemah yotza uvameh einah
yotza. What can an animal carry on שבת and what can an
animal go out with on שבת? Because the same way you're not
allowed to do מלאכה, melakhah, your animal is not allowed to do
מלאכה. melakhah. Now, two important things to mention about this. Number one,
your animal, unless you basically starve it to death or whatever, lock
it up, will do מלאכה melakhah on שבת because it's going to
go out and graze. So it'll be plucking living things on שבת
or whatever. So there's an interesting question about how to define what
types of things, is it basically just like the natural way in
which an animal lives and does like is let to rest, even
though it's technically a מלאכה melakhah as opposed to, you know, things
that are more because of human intervention. But number one there are
ways in which an animal will anyway do one of the ל"ט
מלאכות lamed-tet melachot if that's, it's not interpreted like you might have
thought at the פסוקים, pesukim, rest. It's interpreted through a very halakhic
lens of מלאכה. melakhah. Okay. So that's number one. Number two is
that even if it's not doing מלאכה melakhah for you, like you're
not using it to do work on, there is a פסוק pasuk
that says לא תעשה כל מלאכה אתה ובהמתך, Lo ta'aseh kol melachah
attah uvehemtecha, which is actually using your animal to do work for
you, okay, and in that you have
actually two types of ways. Like if I've got a plow attached
to my animal and I'm pulling my animal
is pulling the plow,
then
I'm really just, it's like
basically I'm plowing on שבת.
It's not even like
I'm transgressing my animal doing מלאכה, melakhah, that's how I do my
plowing. Okay, but let's say my animal is loaded up with something
and I'm like, you know, walking with it and it's carrying or
whatever, that is doing מלאכה melakhah with my animal, I mean that
is like my animal doing מלאכה melakhah for me. That's a particular
prohibition, but in addition to the negative prohibition of doing מלאכה melakhah
for you, there's just a מצווה mitzvah to let your animal rest,
even if it's not doing מלאכה melakhah for me. So for example
the גמרא Gemara. in עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, the משנה Mishnah in
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah says you're not allowed to sell animals to
non-Jews, certain animals, because of a concern that you will rent them
to the non-Jew before שבת and then the non-Jew will use it
on שבת and it'll be still your animal, it won't have transferred
ownership yet and it'll be doing מלאכה melakhah on שבת. So it's
certainly not doing מלאכה melakhah for me, but it's doing מלאכה melakhah
on שבת. I know some of us brought up on those kids'
stories where the rabbi sells his animal to some non-Jew and Anyway,
so okay, anyway, so the animal can't do מלאכה Melacha even if
it's not doing it for you. So how would you define carrying?
So the basic assumption that this משנה Mishnah makes is that anything
that is on the animal that is normally there for the, like
a normal stage of, normally there for its protection is a type
of a clothing. The same way we can wear clothing, animals can
wear clothing. So dogs could have little sweaters. They did not have
horses with little sweaters, but they did have horses that had harnesses
and bits and all those types of things. So what is considered
to be a משא, masoi, like a burden on the animal, what's
considered to be normal clothing? So basically the basic point is something
that you use to the animal to protect, you protect the animal
with it, that's considered clothing and it's not a problem. Something that
it's not protect, it's excessive, not necessary to protect the animal with
is considered a burden and a problem. Even if now it's helping
the animal? Like let's say the animal's cold or something? Okay, so
all right, so we'll see all of that as we continue to
the גמרא. Gemara Let's take a look. במה בהמה יוצאה ובמה אינה
יוצאה. Bameh behemah yotzah uvameh einah yotzah. What can an animal go
out with and what can an animal not go out with? יוצא
הגמל, Yotzah hagamal, the camel can go out with, באפסר, beafsar, with
an אפסר afsar which is, I think it's translated as a harness.
What does the Steinsaltz say there? A bit or a halter. Okay,
a halter, that's what I meant. A halter. Okay, a bit or
a halter. ונאקה, Venaaka, a נאקה naaka which we will find out
which is like a, which is like a female, a white female
camel, בחותם, bechotam, which is another type of a thing around its
mouth. We'll see what these are in the גמרא. Gemara והלובדקים, Vehaluvdikim,
which are these, Libyan donkeys, בפרומביא, beprumbiya, with a פרומביא. prumbiya. We'll
worry about that one when we get to the גמרא. וסוס בשיר,
Vesus bashir, a horse can go out with a שיר, shir, with
a like a collar. וכל בעלי השיר יוצאים בשיר, Vechol baalei hashir
yotzim bashir, any animals that normally you have collars around them can
go out with a collar. ונמשכים בשיר, Venimshachim bashir, and you can
actually, they can be drawn with the collar, meaning basically you attach
a leash to the collar. See where's Rifka when we need her?
She's very sensitive to all these animal issues. ומזין עליהן וטובלין במקומן.
Umazin aleihen vetovlin bimkoman. Now if you have to, that collar became
טמא tamei and you had to sprinkle the ashes of פרה אדומה
parah adumah on it, you could do it even while it's still
attached to the animal, or you had to dunk it into the
מקוה. mikvah. I don't know how, it seems a lot easier to
remove the collar but somehow you're allowed to do it with the
animal, dunking it into the מקוה. mikvah. I hope it's an animal
that can swim. Right. Okay, yes, yes, you asked that it can
go out with its collar, we're going to talk about that. Yeah,
yeah, all of this we will talk about, okay? Okay, so let's
take a look at the גמרא. מאי נאקה בחותם? Mai naaka bechotam?
What does it mean a נאקה naaka can go out with a
חותם? chotam? So אמר רבה בר בר חנה, Amar Rabbah Bar Bar
Chana, נאקתא, naakasa, which is helpful, but basically it means a like
a white female camel. חיוורתי, Chivarti, there, the white, a white female
camel, בזממא דפרזלא, bezmama deparzala, with an iron זממא, zmama, which is,
so רש״י Rashi says a זממא zmama is מוזיא״ל muziel בלע״ז, be-la'az,
which sounds like a muzzle. נוקב את חוטמה ומכניסו בתוכו והוא כמין
טבעת. Nokev et chotamo umachniso betocho vehu kemin tabaat. So it's actually
like a nose ring. Okay, so not exactly a muzzle, but some
type of a, of a nose ring. Now again, the interesting thing
about all of this is is that it would seem that these
types of things, I don't know this, I have to admit I'm
pretty ignorant about these realia here, but it would seem that these
types of things are not to protect it from injury, but either
to protect it from running loose, so maybe that's a form of
protection, you know, you're keeping it protected because under your care it's
protected, right? Or maybe to protect it from damaging somebody else's stuff,
biting or eating somebody else's things. But maybe all of that is
in the category of נטירותא, netiruta, of protection. All right. So that's
what you got
with your white camels with those nose rings, and presumably the other
camel was a type of a bit, something that was doing some
similar type of a function. לובדקים בפרומביא. Luvdikim beprumbiya. So these Libyan
asses with a פרומביא. prumbiya. So אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna,
חמרא לובא, chamra luva, a Libyan ass, although תוספות Tosafot says לובא
luva is Egyptian, but it seems like it's pretty agreed that this
is a Libyan donkey, בפגי דפרזלא, bepagi deparzala, an iron פגי. pagi.
What's a פגי? pagi? So רש״י Rashi says, he gives some explanation
which כני חמור ובית פגי. kanei chamor uveit pagi. What does it
say here? קיבציל, kivtzil, which I've no idea what it is. But
it seems like it's some type of a halter. What does Steinsaltz
say there? A halter? A halter. רש״י Rashi says something like around
the face.
Okay, so some type of an iron halter.
לוי שדר זוזי לבי חוזאי.
Levi shadar zuzei
lebei chuzei.
לוי Levi sent some money to these people לבי חוזאי be-Chuzei למזבן
ליה חמרא לובא lemizban lei chamra luva to go buy for him
some Libyan donkeys. צרו שדרו ליה, Tsaru shadru lei, they wrapped it
up
and they sent the money back to him. ושדרו ליה שערי, veshadru
lei shaari, and they sent back with him also barley. Why?
Because barley is what you feed donkeys. למימר, Lemeimar, the message was
דניגרי דחמרא שערי, denigrei dechamra shaari, that the stepping of a donkey
is with barley, which means that feed barley to donkeys, but the
message was as רש״י Rashi says, don't waste your money on these
Libyan donkeys, they're not worth the effort, buy some donkeys at home,
feed them barley, take it easy, don't try to go after these
fancy Libyan donkeys. Okay, so that was a little bit of a
digression but interesting about how these Libyan donkeys were very maybe wild
or less tamed, needed something more, maybe they were a bigger investment
and they said don't bother yourself with it. Okay, so now the
גמרא goes on. Where were we? נגיד. Nagid. Okay, so אמר רב
יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel, מחליפין לפני רבי machlifin lifnei Rebbe של זו בזו, shel
zo bezo, meaning the students in front of רבי Rebbe asked him,
what about if you switched? Meaning you say A goes out with
X, B goes out with Y, what about A with Y? And
what about A with Y and B with X, right? What about
if you did the other types of things, you switched the things
for the different animals? What would be the הלכה? halacha? So what
would be an example of that? נאקה באפסא, Naaka be'afsa, let's say
it was this white female camel, you wanted to have the regular
bit, not the nose ring. לא תיבעי לך, Lo tiba'i lach, that's
not a question. Why? That certainly is not acceptable. כיון דלא מינטרא
ביה, Keivan d'la mintra bei, it does not do a sufficient job
of protecting it. משוי הוא, Masui hu, that's considered to be a
burden. So anything that's insufficient has no purpose being on the animal
and therefore is considered a burden. So this white female camel is
obviously harder to tame or harder to control. So if you do
a lesser thing it certainly doesn't work. כי תיבעי לך, Ki tiba'i
lach, where should you be asking your question? גמל בחותם. Gamal bechotam.
You have your normal camel and the question is using this nose
ring which normally you wouldn't bother with with a normal camel. בחותם.
Bechotam. מאי? Mai? What's the הלכה? כיון דסגי ליה באפסא, Keivan d'sagi
lei be'afsa, משוי הוא. masui hu. Since this אפסא, afsa, this bit
would suffice, if you do it if it's something excessive that's considered
a burden. או דילמא נטירותא יתירתא לא אמרינן משוי הוא. O dilma
netiruta yetira la amrinan masui hu. Since it's basically just doing a
better job, we're not going to say that it is a burden.
It's basically still doing a job, maybe it's not fully needed but
look, it's there for a purpose and it's protecting the animal, so
therefore it is not considered a burden. Not necessarily sufficient. Right. So
what is the story? So that's going to be the focus right
now about נטירותא יתירתא, netiruta yetira, something that's doing an extra job
of protecting. So אמר לפניו רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי, Amar lifanav
Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yossi, so רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yishmael bar Rabbi Yossi, right, from we just had him already today,
so once again רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi
Yossi is responding to רבי. Rebbe. כך אמר אבא, Kach amar Abba,
this is what my father said. Very nice how we have those
parallels, right? רבי Rebbe and then רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yishmael bar Rabbi Yossi talking about what his father רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi said. This is what my father said. ארבע בהמות יוצאות באפסא.
Arba behemot yotzot be'afsa. Four animals go out with this bit. הסוס,
Hasus, a horse, והפרד, ve'hapered, the mule, I think פרד pered is
mule, right? We'll say והפרד ve'hapered is mule, mule, והגמל, ve'hagamal, the
camel, והחמור, ve'hachamor, a donkey. ולמעוטי מאי? U'l'ma'utei mai? So what is
this coming to exclude? לאו למעוטי גמל בחותם? Lav l'ma'utei gamal bechotam?
Presumably it means these animals only a bit is okay, nothing else
is okay. So isn't that what it's saying? So the answer is
לא, no, that's not what it sounds like. It sounds like it's
not limiting other things with this animal, it's limiting other animals with
this. לא, למעוטי נאקה באפסא. l'ma'utei naaka be'afsa. So no, we're coming
to exclude that that only these animals does the bit suffice, but
of this white donkey, this white camel, this נאקה, naaka, the bit
is not sufficient. So these four with a bit does not say
other things don't work with these four. It says other animals a
bit is not sufficient and a bit is not acceptable. במתניתא תנא,
Bematnita tana, in a ברייתא Braitah we taught, לובדקים וגמל יוצאים באפסא,
Luvdekim v'gamal yotzim be'afsa, that the these Libyan donkeys and the camel
can both go out with the bit. Okay, so it goes so
fine, that just our משנה Mishnah mentioned the Libyan donkeys with the
פרומביא, proumbiya, which is like a halter, and here it says a
bit also works for these. So תוספות Tosafot by the way points
out, why hasn't that answered our question? Because if a bit works
and a halter works, then obviously something that's a little bit more
than necessary, so תוספות says, look, there's a range. There's something that
this is okay, but this is even better. There's a range where
it's like you this is what you normally would do to do
an even better protection. But what happens when you go beyond that
range? You do something which is clearly considered to be excessive. Okay,
not really not necessary, but it does protect it more, but it's
really not necessary. That's the question. במתניתא תנא, Bematnita tana, in a
ברייתא Braitah we taught. קתנאי. Katannai. This question about excessive protection is
a קתנאי. Katannai. אין חיה יוצאת בסוגר, Ein chaya yotzet besoger, an
animal cannot go out with a סוגר soger which basically is a
collar, חנניה אומר יוצאת בסוגר, Chananya omer yotzet besoger, can go out
with a collar, ובכל דבר המשתמר u'v'chol davar hamishtamer and anything that'll
protect it. במאי עסקינן? Bemai askinan? What what are we talking about?
אילימא בחיה גדולה? Ilima bechaya gedola? If you're talking about a large
animal like I don't know, a bear, so מי סגי לה סוגר?
mi sagi lah soger? Since when is a collar sufficient? That's what
רש״י Rashi says. Since when is a collar sufficient? Obviously you can't
go out with a collar, that's not doing anything. אלא בחיה קטנה,
Ela bechaya ktana, a small animal like רש״י Rashi says like I
don't know like a weasel or something. So we would say a
dog, right? Anyway, מי לא סגי לה בסוגר? mi lo sagi lah
besoger? Of course a collar is sufficient, that's exactly the... Exactly what
you use to keep it from running away. אלא לאו חתול איכא
בינייהו, Ella lav chatul ika beineihu, it's a cat. Now a cat
you would think is exactly this example of a small animal. So
רש״י Rashi says, but cats don't even really need collars, cats don't
go running away. How's the cat? What do you guys say about
that? All right, anyway, רש״י Rashi says שאינו תאב לברוח כל כך,
she-eino ta-eiv livro-ach kol kach, it's not so interested in running away.
No, you don't think that's correct? All right, I don't know. Anyway,
תנא קמא סבר, Tanna Kamma savar, כיון דסגי ליה במתנא בעלמא, keivan
de-sagi lei be-mitna be-alma, since normally a little string would be enough,
you don't really need this סוגר, soger, this like serious collar, so
therefore משוי הוא, massui hu, a serious collar is unnecessary and it's
a burden, it's excessive. וחנניה סבר, ve-Chananya savar, and Chananya says כל
נטירות יתירה לא אמרינן משוי הוא, kol netirot yeteira lo amrinan massui
hu, even if it's excessive, it is not a משוי, massui, it's
doing the job. So therefore the גמרא wants
to read that this debate, it's not clear exactly what they're talking
about, is a debate
of when you do something excessive, is that a problem? אמר רב
הונא בר חייא אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Huna bar Chiya amar Shmuel,
הלכה כחנניה, halacha ke-Chananya, we rule like חנניה, Chananya, even if you
do an extra something that's more than necessary, it's not considered a
burden. לוי בריה דרב הונא בר חייא ורבה בר רב הונא Levi
berei de-Rav Huna bar Chiya ve-Rabba bar Rav Huna הוו קאזלי באורחא,
havei ka-azlei be-orcha, so they, these two were going on the way.
קדמי חמרא דלוי לחמרא דרבה בר רב הונא, Kadmi chamra de-Levi le-chamra
de-Rabba bar Rav Huna, Levi's donkey stepped in front of רבה בר
רב הונא's Rabba bar Rav Huna donkey, and רבה בר רב הונא
Rabba bar Rav Huna was clearly the senior person and the one
that was afforded more respect. So חלש דעתיה דרבה בר רב הונא.
chalash daiteih de-Rabba bar Rav Huna. So רבה בר רב הונא Rabba
bar Rav Huna felt bad, he says Levi doesn't respect me, his
donkey walked in front of me. So אימא ליה מילתא, eima lei
milta, so Levi figures, you know what, let me say something to
him, כי היכי דאיתיתיב דעתיה, ki heichi di-iteseiv daiteih, to make רבה
בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna feel better, I want to
make it clear that my donkey didn't do it on purpose and
I didn't do it on purpose, okay? So here's what Levi said
to רבה בר רב הונא, Rabba bar Rav Huna, he said אמר
ליה, amar lei, so he said to רבה בר רב הונא, Rabba
bar Rav Huna, חמור שאסקב רעיין כגון זה, chamor she-askav ra-in kiggon
zeh, if you have a donkey that doesn't behave like this donkey
that walked in front of you, מהו לצאת בפומביא בשבת, mahu litzet
be-pumbiya be-Shabbat, can you have it go out with a פומביא, pumbiya,
with this, you know, with this bigger, with this like type of
a halter on שבת? Maybe that would not be considered excessive because
this is a donkey that needs more control, a rebellious donkey needs
more controlling. So it was a good way, look, notice he did
two things: he made it clear that the donkey was acting, you
know, sort of not being controlled, you know, not acting according to
his wishes, and number two is he made himself, he showed that
he was the תלמיד talmid and the other was the רב, rav,
because he was asking him a halachic שאלה. shaila. So it's very
smart. So אמר ליה, amar lei, הכי אמר אבוך משמיה דשמואל, hachi
amar avuch mishmei de-Shmuel, here's what your father says in the name
of שמואל, Shmuel, הלכה כחנניה, halacha ke-Chananya, we rule like חנניה, Chananya,
so actually you would be able to go out on שבת. It
doesn't tell us whether he felt good that the, you know, now
he felt okay, but presumably yes. So anyway we will continue tomorrow
with this discussion on שבת, with this discussion about going out animals
and what they can wear on שבת.